<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of ecclesiasticall and politike povver Shewing, the church is a monarchicall gouernment, ordained to a supernaturall and spirituall end, tempered with an aristocraticall order, (which is the best of all and most conformable to nature) by the great pastor of soules Iesus Christ. Faithfully translated out of the Latin originall, of late publikely printed and allowed in Paris. Now set foorth for a further warrant and encouragement to the Romish Catholikes of England, for theyr taking of the Oath of Allegiance; seeing so many others of their owne profession in other countries doe deny the Popes infalibility in indgement and temporall power ouer princes, directly against the doctrine of Iesuits. To the prince.</title>
            <title>De ecclesiastica et politica potestate. English</title>
            <author>Richer, Edmond.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1612</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10748</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102957</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838716</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838716</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3104</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10748)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3104)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1152:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of ecclesiasticall and politike povver Shewing, the church is a monarchicall gouernment, ordained to a supernaturall and spirituall end, tempered with an aristocraticall order, (which is the best of all and most conformable to nature) by the great pastor of soules Iesus Christ. Faithfully translated out of the Latin originall, of late publikely printed and allowed in Paris. Now set foorth for a further warrant and encouragement to the Romish Catholikes of England, for theyr taking of the Oath of Allegiance; seeing so many others of their owne profession in other countries doe deny the Popes infalibility in indgement and temporall power ouer princes, directly against the doctrine of Iesuits. To the prince.</title>
                  <title>De ecclesiastica et politica potestate. English</title>
                  <author>Richer, Edmond.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by VV. S[tansby] and are to be sold by Iohn Budge, at the great south doore of Paules, and at Britaines Bursse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1612.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Richer, Edmond.  De ecclesiastica et politica potestate.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church. --  Government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Gallicanism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3104:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE of Eccleſiaſticall and Politike povver.</p>
            <p>SHEWING, The Church is a Monarchicall <hi>go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, ordained to a ſupernaturall and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall</hi> end, tempered with an ariſtocraticall or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, (which is the beſt of all and moſt conformable to nature) by the great Paſtor of ſoules Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Faithfully tranſlated out of the Latin originall, of late pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blikely printed and allowed in Paris.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now ſet foorth for a further warrant</hi> and encouragement to the Romiſh Catholikes of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, for theyr taking of the Oath of Allegiance; ſeeing ſo many others of their owne profeſſion in other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries doe deny the Popes infalibility in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and temporall power ouer Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, directly againſt the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Ieſuits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the PRINCE.</p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>VV.S.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Budge,</hi> at the great South doore of Paules, and at Britaines Burſſe. 1612.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3104:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3104:2"/>
            <head>To the Prince.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe are not now idle fancies of mine owne, hot ebullitions of a French bloud, youthfully ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the charge long before the combate; No nor of any one man alone, neuer ſo wiſe, neuer ſo temperat. They are the graue diſputations, the ſound deciſions of a whole compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, one of the moſt famous, as one of the moſt aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in the world, for diuine and humane learning: Who now ſets forth to the open view of all men what their opinion is about the Popes either lawfull or vnlawfull authoritie. No more are they any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular imaginations, or exact concluſions of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, the Popes open aduerſaries, or ſome other (if there be any) of his violent enemies; who, perhaps to forward in their owne way, deny vtterly all the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of the Biſhop of Rome, becauſe he hath vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb facs="tcp:3104:3"/>
too much, and would haue Rome totally ruyned becauſe there are many abuſes therein; and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be reformed by good lawes, reducing order &amp; conueniency to their own auncient iuſt and lawfull vſe: Much like vnto that people, that wholy forbids the vſe of that good creature of God, wine, becauſe hurtfull by accident, rather then to temper his furie with water, or moderate the quantity. They are, I ſay, the too too gentle, the too too indulgent determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Popes beſt friends, of his dereſt darlings, nay, of his owne ſtrongeſt ſupport in Fraunce, by whome he raignes yet there, and without whom he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not haue an inch of credit in that whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: Determinations, which yet ſeeming to make good the reaſons of <hi>the French Herald,</hi> &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude, <hi>ex obliquo</hi> at leaſt, to his <hi>Croiſade,</hi> makes mee the bolder to tender this vnto your Highnes, to whome that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was alſo dedicated: As a confirmation now by theſe wiſe men, of thoſe reaſons which, as his owne, he did at that time eſteeme more fooliſh, then for the reſpect due vnto the aſſent of ſuch perſons, hee dares euer hold them hereafter. For indeed what ſhold we not boldly execute againſt him, that with fier and ſword, open inuaſion and ſecret treaſons, declares himſelfe ſo violent and bloudy an enemie to vs, though we not to him? Wee, I ſay, right reformed Chriſtians and Catholiks who, rightly lightned with the ſhining truth of the ſpirit and the Scripture, haue ſo lawfully ſhaken off that moſt vniuſt, moſt vnſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable iron-yoake of later yeares forged in the Church of Rome; when wee ſee his owne men, his
<pb facs="tcp:3104:3"/>
owne maintainers ſo flatly condemne him? But alas! what order to bee taken? I am not able to giue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, much leſſe to commaund. Onely this, my moſt harty prayer vnto the Almightie ſhal be, &amp; as long as I breath I will neuer finiſh it, till it bee finiſhed or my ſelfe; That now when it ſeemes that in theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter daies, by frequent diſputations the truth beginnes to cleere it ſelfe of thoſe darke clouds of ignorance, and thicke vayles wherein it had beene hitherto pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely wrapt and ouercaſt; Now that it ſeemes that all Chriſtians of all profeſſions, at leaſt thoſe of the better ſort among them, draw neerer then euer they did one to another, and all to that happy <hi>medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> wherein conſiſts the true and onely hope of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral reconciliation, it may pleaſe his heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſtirre vp, and ſtrongly moue all Chriſtian Princes and Magiſtrates, as well Eccleſiaſticall as Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, to call together a good lawful and free Councel, as generall as may bee; wherein all abſolute and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie points to ſaluation, being conſiderately with brotherly loue, and without animoſity diſcuſſed, wee may with common conſent of all, frame together a conſtant ſubſtantiall and vniuerſall profeſſion of our faith: As without doubt it would be a thing moſt fit to preuent and auoid many ſcandals, and eaſie enogh to be attained vnto, if euerie one would leaue all pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptorineſſe of his owne ſence, and cleaue to the right naked and vnpaſſionate truth. It remaining, for the reſt, lawfull to euerie nationall Church, in things indifferent and not altogether abſolute and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to ſaluation, differently to beleeue according to
<pb facs="tcp:3104:4"/>
their beſt aduiſe and Chriſtian libertie. It is a thing which (after God) wee muſt ſolely and onely hope from the hands of that thrice-great King your royall father, hee hauing a particular right to it by his title of Defender of the Faith, as indeed hee makes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe euerie day more and more worthy of the ſame, both abroad &amp; at home, carefully ſuppreſſing here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en in their birth, there by his credit, heere by his commaund, there by his word of aduice, here by his ſword of Iuſtice. Oh! what helpe our famous <hi>Henry the Great</hi> would alſo haue yeelded to this, if thoſe that did ſmell out ſome ſuch purpoſe in him, had not, as vnluckely as traiterouſly ſhortned his daies.</p>
            <p>But in that happie aſſembly let it not be forgotten for the firſt point and ground of all the following good, to giue backe againe to the Catholike Church her ancient right and authoritie; clipping the Popes wings of ſo much as he hath moſt tyrannouſly vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and reduced vniuerſallity to his own particular. For otherwiſe, as long as that tyrannical, vnbridled, monſtruous, impious, omnipotency (which none can tell yet how far it runneth, or can ſtretch it ſelfe,) be not limited within the bounds of reaſon, I meane of the law of God, there is no hope of reconciliation, no hope euer of any good at all. I doe not deny that the Biſhop of Rome hath altogether no authoritie as from God; Neither but that he may haue a great deale more by the free graunt of Councels, or by the liberallitie of Princes. That which hee hath as from God, let him keepe it ſtill in Gods name; <hi>The gifts of
<pb facs="tcp:3104:4"/>
God are without repentance.</hi> Yea,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.29.</note> let him keepe that which he hath lawfully receiued of auncient Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, as the firſt place among the fiue Patriarkes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene whome the care of all the Churches of the world was friendly and almoſt equally diuided, and to him by eſpeciall aſſigned the care of theſe Weſt-churches; In which reſpect only the King makes no difficultie to call the church of Rome,<note place="margin">In his Maieſties firſt ſpeech to the Parliament.</note> our Mother-church. Let him alſo keepe that which auncient god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Princes haue giuen him, though he cannot ſhow, nor who, nor how, nor when: ſo that he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it, at leaſt, vſe it as a free gift, and not like a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate vngratefull rebell, to the preiudice of the heyrs of his benefactors. For in that caſe the gifts of Princes are not as the gifts of God, and, be they neuer ſo firmely ſealed, neuer ſo auncient, or pleading pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, are euer and moſt lawfully ſubiect to a iuſt reſumption. But if ſtill through ſhame or mallice he be loth to accept of theſe moſt reaſonable termes, &amp; be brought againe to his firſt eſtate, thogh glorious enough for any temperate ambition; I meane to that which hee hath by the foure former generall Councels, and by the Emperours of thoſe times (for otherwiſe to reduce him to that which hee hath by S. <hi>Peter,</hi> (if euen hee haue any thing by S. <hi>Peter</hi>) it were but a poore and verie beggerlie thing: Finally if hee will not voluntarily forgoe all vſurpation or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, neuer ſo auncient or moderne, let him be moſt iuſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> depriued thereof, as a preuaricator, and bee brought by meere force to that which he ſhould vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily and wiſely yeeld vnto by right. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:3104:5"/>
ſtrengthned now the more with the opinions of that famous Societie, which is no leſſe then a little continually ſtanding Councell in France, allowed by the Pope himſelfe, I conclude ſtill with <hi>the French Herald,</hi> to a generall <hi>Croiſade</hi> againſt him that is now become the great enemy of Chriſtendome; And that the executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the decrees of that bleſſed coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell being put into your Princely hands, as the Lief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant general of the high Defender of the faith, the whole Catholike Church, ſighing and panting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the heauy loade of that cruell tyranny, may for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be beholding to your valor, and extoll you as the reſtorer of her liberty. Vp then, vp, braue Prince; the eyes of all Chriſtendome are now caſt vpon you, to ſee you beginne; you ſhall not want friends and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, euen more then you thinke, euen more then perhaps you looke for. Thoſe that now dare not ſhew their heads for want of a Generall, will mount vpon the talleſt courſers they can finde to ſhew their whole body, and draw with more haſt to bee neareſt to you; At leaſt you ſhal know who be your friends. For if the firſt blow be not giuen vnto that monſter by your Royal father, and the ſecond and laſt by your ſelfe; ſure, ſure, I knowe not who will beginne, much leſſe who ſhall make an end. And leaſt any man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that I ſtand yet wilfully and without iuſt cauſes in my old vaine; or that I perſwade you vpon the reaſons of ſtrangers, or any moderne writers onelie; I end with an inſtance of your owne, a graue prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie or a ſentence, if you will, giuen in this caſe almoſt foure hundred yeares ſince, by a right reuerend, god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:3104:5"/>
biſhop of yours, <hi>Robert of Lincolne,</hi> altogether out of likely-hood to ſauor any thing of the hot French, or of the intereſſed Proteſtant. Another man of yours, your auncient and learned <hi>Mat. Paris</hi> citeth it,<note place="margin">In Henrico iii. An. <hi>1153.</hi>
               </note> out of whoſe bookes I could bring almoſt as many arguments to this purpoſe, as there are leaues, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer otherwiſe a paſſionate mainteiner of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike ſea. That good old Prelate dying in a full age, after that he had liued and ſerued here vnder the tyranny of three or foure Popes, <hi>Gregory</hi> 9. <hi>Celeſtin</hi> 4. <hi>Innocent</hi> 4. hauing held a long diſcourſe with his Prieſts and Clergie the ſame night that hee dyed, in complaint of the hard and miſerable eſtate of the Church in thoſe times, accuſing the Popes onely, as the totall cauſe thereof, and calling them Heretikes and Antichriſts, at laſt did willingly yeeld vp his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſoule (the neerer to happineſſe, the ſharper-ſighted and ſurer in her iudgements) with great vehemencie, ſending foorth this laſt Oracle from the bottome of his heart. <hi>The Church ſhall neuer be deliuered out of this Egiptian bondage, vnleſſe it be by the mouth of the bloody ſword.</hi> To the ſword then,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> to the ſword, I durſt almoſt ſay euen at this inſtant, for at laſt when Councell and all is done, wee ſhall euer bee put to it. Poſſeſſion is very ſweet; and that Iudicious man, beſt acquainted with the humour of Popes, knew full well that they doe not part ſo eaſily from what they haue once catched holde of. If all this doe not ſatisfie the worlde, truely then I knowe not what ſhall, though I knowe very well what ſhould; howbeit hardlie of
<pb facs="tcp:3104:6"/>
more weight then that which is handled through all this Booke. Finally, to the end none may ſay that I am more ready to talke then to doe, I vow faithfully that if euer this holie purpoſe goe forward, and God let me enioy my ſelfe, I ſhall be one of the forwardeſt, in my poore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to ſhew by my beſt ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours in life or death, how much I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Highneſſes <hi>Moſt humble, moſt faithfull and moſt deuoted ſeruant</hi> Δ</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="to_Catholics">
            <pb facs="tcp:3104:6"/>
            <head>To the Romiſh Catholikes of <hi>England.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt deere, though but halfe bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, whom yet I wholly loue, euen though you were but men, a great deale more being Chriſtians, moſt of all, being Engliſh Christians, and ſubiects to that great Monarch, my adoptiue Maſter; who hauing beene ſo gracious vnto me, farre, farre beyond my deſerts or any hope I might euer haue builded thereon, hath bound me for euer to apply, vow &amp; dedicate all my life, ſtudies, ſeruice and best endeuours to him and for him, and for his ſake to all ſuch as are his:<note place="margin">In his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties firſt ſpeech to the Parliament.</note> whom, euen for that reſpect only, I muſt needs loue, thogh they were but halfe his, as long as hee wants the best part of them, that is their ſoules, as he himſelfe in ſome place ſaith of your ſelues.</p>
            <p>In that reſolution, &amp; for as much as the whole need not the Phiſition, and that indeed I am no Phiſition at all, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to God and themſelues that other part of the good
<pb facs="tcp:3104:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
people of this famous kingdom, which agreeth in faith and beleefe with vs; And chooſing you, as the fitteſt obiect for my loue and ſeruice to work vpon, and in you that beſt part of you, your ſoules: yea, euen in that leauing that gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter buſineſſe of your whole conuerſion for ſpiritual things, to the working care of that ſo worthy <hi>Abbot,</hi> who hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to be a more worthy Archbiſhop and Prim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te of ſo flouriſhing a Church, Of an eloquent <hi>King</hi> of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don, Of an acute indeed, and much acute <hi>Montaign</hi> of Bathes and Wels; Of that other learned <hi>Abbot,</hi> Of that right diuine &amp; Iudicious <hi>Leyfield,</hi> Of ſubſtantiall and fruitful <hi>Field;</hi> yea, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring to leaue you to the liuely remains of a rich En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh <hi>Iewel,</hi> Of a ſolid <hi>Hooker,</hi> ſo skilful, that with one only hook he fiſheth of both ſides, with many others, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liue &amp; a ſleep, ſo eaſie to be found, ſo hard to be nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bred; &amp; medling onely in temporalty and ſuch things as are and haue euer beene receiued for conſtant and common religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thorough all the world, but onely ſome few yeres ſince, that the diuell, being almoſt at a bay, ſtrugleth with his laſt and moſt violent endeuours, againſt the truth that ſtrangleth him; Neuertheleſſe medling heerein more for your own good, then for his Maieſties, which yet as a right <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> as a kind <hi>Pater-familias</hi> of the Common-wealth, hee will euer eſteeme his owne when it is yours: I thought ſome moneths a goe to haue preſented you in your owne language that famous letter of a great friend of yours, the Ieſuit <hi>Cotton,</hi> written in French to the Queene Regent of Fraunce in diſalowance of <hi>Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naes</hi> booke, and other writings of other Ieſuits, approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing diſobedience of ſubiects to their own lawful kings, in temporall matters, euen to their poiſoning and murther.
<pb facs="tcp:3104:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
But another man with more haſt then good ſpeede (I am ſure) though not with a better minde then my ſelfe, ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it vnto you in another diſh and with a ſower ſauce in the end, of that odious chamber of meditations, did quite marre the good vſe that yee both and wee, I meane the whole ſtate, might very well haue reapt therof. All things are not fit to bee ſaid at all times, neither ought we ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly to vncouer the ſhame of our brethren as long as ther is any hope of amendment, principally being moſt certain that the beſt part of you doth not alow, yea, I dare ſay, not know thoſe abhominable, execrable and almoſt incredible courſes. For no doubt but it would haue made ſome impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in your harts, to haue ſeene (without ſuch a bitter ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, quite then out of ſeaſon, and rather to exaſperate then to pacifie you) ſo famous a man, a Ieſuit by profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and one of your greater ſaints, writing of ſet purpoſe to ſo eminent a perſon, and impugning whatſoeuer hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath beene, or hereafter might be, written by any of his owne order, or by others, against the temporall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Princes ouer their ſubiects; cyting orderlie one by one, as <hi>numerus certus pro incerto</hi> a doze<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Ieſuits, Cardinall <hi>Tolet,</hi> Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine, Gregory of Valencia, Salmeron, Delrio, Heyſſius, Becanus, Gretzerus, Leſsius, Serrerius, Azor, Richeom,</hi> euerie one with ſome ſpeciall place mainteining the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces temporall authoritie. And for better fortifying ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſetting downe of himſelfe, and without any vrging, <hi>15.</hi> heads and principles of the faith, and beleefe of their whole ſociety about that matter whereof among the reſt, the <hi>6. 7. 8 9. 10. 11. 12.</hi> are theſe, after that in the former he hath eſtabliſhed and highly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended the monarchicall
<pb facs="tcp:3104:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſtate, as the beſt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> That kings are annointed, and therefore called the annointed of the Lord, that euerie one (as <hi>Simeon</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of Theſſalonica ſaith) may vnderſtand that they ought to be inuiolable, and reſpected as holy and ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> That whoſoeuer reſiſteth them or rebelleth againſt them, ſhall receiue their owne damnation; <hi>Rom. 13.2.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> That obedience is due vnto them, not becauſe vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, wiſe, mighty, or of any other ſuch qualities, but meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe they be kings and eſtabliſhed by God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> That it is not lawful to deny them their obedience, much leſſe to rebell against them, though they ſhould bee v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tous froward and hard to be endured; <hi>1. Pet. 2.18.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> That in ſuch caſes wee ought to pray for them as the Prophet did command the Iewes for <hi>Nebucadnezar,</hi> and <hi>Baltazar Bar. i. ii.</hi> And that thoſe perſecutions, loſses of goods, and other afflictions which are patiently ſuffered for that cauſe, and without rebellion againſt their ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, are things moſt pleaſing to God, and agreeable to that praiſe which Paul giueth to the Ebrewes, cap. <hi>10.34.</hi> and to that ordinance by himſelfe publiſhed in the Church. <hi>Rom. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> That it is not lawfull to attempt any thing againſt their perſons; but that it is a moſt execrable parricide, a prodigious crime and abominable ſacriledge.</p>
            <p>All which articles and letter, though by ſome, accuſed of ſome equiuocation, truely at least by all honeſt plaine-dealing men and fully good ſubiects, of to much ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and cohibition in a matter which deſerued with an open mouth to haue bene more clearely and largely exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded;
<pb facs="tcp:3104:8"/>
yet willing to take al things in the beſt ſence, euen in our aduerſaries, and receiue as lawfull and current, the coyne of ill pay-maſters, neuer ſo baſe, neuer ſo clipt, ſo it be but indifferent good: I then purpoſed with a peaceful, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, and truely Chriſtian and brotherly mind and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, to ſet them before your eyes, to the end you might with as peacefull a ſpirit, and not ſtirred or diſtaſted by any vnſauory appendix, conceaue at leaſt of this point, That ſo many other Ieſuits of other nations are not of the ſame opinion in that behalfe with your <hi>Parſons, Campi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Creſwell, Garnet, Hall, Greenwell, Gerard, Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> &amp; other your fiery Ieſuits; which as right Puritans among their other fellowes, that is <hi>abſtractum de ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracto,</hi> (as though England were the onely Seminary in the world, for ſuch a cumberſome, to ſharp-ſighted, and to ſharp-minded zeale) defin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng and refining law and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell according to their owne humours and priuate ends, till they haue (I feare me, and God forbid) finiſhed and diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued all, make Religion where there is none, and irreligion of that which is most ſacred and religious: As by all lawes both diuine, naturall, Eccleſiaſticall, politike and poſitiue, temporal obedience of ſubiects to their Princes is, and hath euer beene held.</p>
            <p>But that good duetie being intercepted, as I told you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I had very willingly requited it by preſenting you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other booke of another, though yet my Country-man, ſtill of your owne profeſſion, for with other armes will I neuer vrge you, then thoſe that your owne men ſhall put into my hands; A man truly moſt worthy and learned, A booke most worth reading, intituled <hi>Of the common offence and priuiledged caſe,</hi> wherein ſhewing by degrees, and
<pb facs="tcp:3104:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
from age to age, the incroaching increaſe of the authority of the Popes and Church-men, in that old time of thick ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, when ſcarce any in the world but they could reade or write his name, that Author moſt excellently proueth that <hi>a principio non erat ſic,</hi> and that from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; many hundred yeares after, al Church-men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception were ſubiect to the ful obedience and Iuſtice of their ciuill Princes, till by their fauourable graunt and relaxation, or rather by an ouer-religious ſtat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſse, vnprouidency and ſcrupulous ſimplicitie, Church-men by tract of time got to be releaſed in ſome caſes; from whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce firſt aroſe the diſtinction, betwixt <hi>delictum commune &amp; caſus priuilegiatus</hi> as they call them.</p>
            <p>But fearing leaſt that booke neuer ſo cleer, neuer ſo wel followed, might not be of great moment with you, as being written by a priuate man, not perhaps ſo famous among you as your owne father <hi>Cotton,</hi> though a noble Iudge of one of our high Courts of Parliament, and his booke o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly printed, allowed and licenced by Catholike learned Diuines I thought rather to looke for a better opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; which, I am ſure, hath not bene euer ſince ſo effectuall as this, nor perhaps will be a long time hereafter. For vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be in a generall Councel, it is not to be hoped that you may euer haue a conſtant reſolution of ſo many &amp; ſo learned Doctors of your own &amp; aboue all ſo little intereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in your caſe, but rather which being able to claim more then you, as being Church-men theſelues, diſclaim honest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; willingly that which is not theirs, the more therfore to be beleeued. It is no more <hi>Luther</hi> that ſpeakes in Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia, <hi>Caluin</hi> in Geneua, <hi>Henry 8.</hi> in England, <hi>Iames the ſixt,</hi> in Scotland; you cannot impute this to any parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb facs="tcp:3104:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
quarrell, or hereſie. They are not priuate men of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Countrie that ſpeake in their owne ſence, and of which you might ſay they may ouerſhoot themſelues, thogh of your owne profeſsion, as the two aboue mentioned. It is not one <hi>Blackwel</hi> your Archprieſt, one <hi>VVarmington,</hi> one <hi>Sheldon,</hi> your Prieſts, of whome you might ſay the two former were priſoners, the laſt a Runne-away. <hi>VVid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi> at leaſt was free, that ſo learnedly confutes <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe, and is your own ſtil, yea moſt paſsionate; as the faſhion is of all thoſe that haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken vs, therefore the more worthy to be credited by you. Though it be a great wonder how he hath beene able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue ſtill ſo much reaſon and honeſty to make a ſtop there, ſince it is not the good hap of ſuch as fall once from the ſteepe rocke of the truth, to graspe any where, but rather alwaies to tumble from an error to an hereſie, till they be, legges and lims all broken, ouerwhelmed in the bottome or rather in the bottomleſſe pit; yet it is not hee that ſpeakes It is not <hi>the King himſelfe,</hi> of whome you might ſay he ſpeakes in his owne cauſe, though no otherwiſe then a good Father, commending naturall duety to his belooued Children, And, I pray you, who ſhal looſe moſt, or be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed at laſt, either the godly father for admoniſhing his rebellious children, or they for denying him his due? It is not that ſo powerfully <hi>fulmino<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in vanos illos fulmina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores et vacua fulmina Capitolij,</hi> learned <hi>Andrewes,</hi> or any other of our graue men; of whome you might ſay, they ſpeake to pleaſe the King. They are free and franke Frenchmen that ſpeake, in Fraunce it ſelfe, the mother of all fraunchiſe and freedome; free, not onely in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but without preiudice in their mindes. For of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:3104:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Frenchmen they are not that part, which, being neerer in faith to vs heere, you might perhaps nick-name Puritans, open and oppoſite enemies to the Pope; No ſuch matter; They are your owne deere Brethren, rather then our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> friends, the ſame ſheep of one pretended fold with your ſelues, the Popes moſt obedient and gentle children: who rather by too gracious &amp; charitable a granting, then by a reſtraining maner, rather giue a new far ſtretched power to your common father, then abridge him of any of his old. It is, I ſay, whole France that ſpeakes by her <hi>Sorbonne,</hi> &amp; that whole ſociety agreeing together as one man ſpeaks alſo by one man, their Sindick &amp; learned Speaker <hi>Riche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> very wel known though not named: The <hi>Sorbonne</hi> of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris, I ſay, ſo famous through all Chriſtendome, &amp; which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an ancient co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of the moſt graue &amp; learned French doctors in Diuinity, &amp; both canonicall and ciuill law, is, as it were, a continual ſtanding councell in France allowed by the Pope, at leaſt repreſents it as long as there is none elſe; and to their oracles, in that reſpect, all France in a time of neede, yea verte often many forraine Countries haue had their refuge. For eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when at the firſt this very ſame book came forth without a name, as a child expoſd to fortun, that it might be the more free to any to oppoſe &amp; alleadge what they would, what they could againſt it; Then indeede the Nuncio, perceiuing his maſter ſo thoroughly let blood, not onely in his <hi>Cefalica</hi> or <hi>Baſilica,</hi> that is in his headſhip ouer the church, or royaltie ouer Princes, but euen in his <hi>Arteria magna,</hi> wherein conſiſts the life and the ſpirit of all his being, runs in a great heate to diuers Biſhops and Cardinals; and gathering as many as he could to accompany one, the greateſt indeed among them all, willing nilling (as
<pb facs="tcp:3104:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
one that truly hath euer bin very moderate, but yet hath ſo neere an intereſt in the Pope, both by oth &amp; by hope he may wel haue to be a Pope himſelfe one day, is, ſure, he is more worthy of the place, then the place, as now it is, of him) ſends him in al the haſt to complaine to the Counſel, and demand the ſuppreſſion of this booke. But that right worthy of that name <hi>Henry de Bourbon,</hi> moſt worthily the firſt Prince of the bloud, hauing thoroughly peruſed it before hand, vndertakes brauely the defence thereof &amp;, in the behalfe of our yong <hi>Lewes</hi> his Lord &amp; neere kinſman, ouerthrows the reaſons without reaſon, of the Biſhops, Cardinall &amp; all, giuing by authoritie of the whole Counſell, more autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to the booke then it had before. For e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en that other eye of France <hi>Charles de Bourbon,</hi> Earle of Soiſſons, taking then first notice of the booke, &amp; therfore not able to ſpeake much to it, but vpon the aſſurance of his nephews ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, cauſed it purpoſely to be tranſlated to vnderſtand it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and finding it alſo moſt iuſt, equitable and well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, it was publikely printed in French, whereas it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore but in Latin. Then was <hi>Sorbonne</hi> alſo conſulted (as they vſe in ſuch caſes) which gaue freely their opinion in fauor of the book, as knowing ful wel from whence it came, &amp; beginning the, as it were, to auow it as their own. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Nuncioes crew yet not yeelding, but continuing to gather, it ſelfe together three or foure daies to aduiſe of ſome means for their redreſſe, as ſoon as that famous high Court of Parliament of Paris, the right arme of our Kings, &amp; in ſome ſort Protectors of the kingdom in a nonage, had notice of it, they ſent immediately the kings Atturny gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to bid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon pain of the Kings diſpleaſure to ſeparate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; leaue off ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenticles, which were not only
<pb facs="tcp:3104:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
without, but againſt the Kings authority, &amp; of the Church about ſuch things as were allowed by his Maiesties most honourable priu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Counſell, by the Sorbonne, and by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, them three repreſenting, as it were, the three E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates, that is to ſay the whole kingdome.</p>
            <p>And now that which that <hi>moſt Chriſtian Fraunce</hi> ſaith, is nothing new, or of her own ſelfe, but <hi>Sereniſsime Venice</hi> hath ſaid as much vpon mature conſultation of al her Diuines, and ſaith ſo still; <hi>Catholike Spain</hi> it ſelfe thinking no leſſe: which yet hath ſpoken ſometimes as far as any of the reſt, if not further, as their owne mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Councils held at Toledo, moſt learnedly cited in that Royall <hi>Apology for the Oath of Allegiance,</hi> do mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly iterate and teſtifie. <hi>Fraunce, Spaine and Venice,</hi> the three <hi>Charites,</hi> the three minions of the Pope, that yet ſticke moſt ſtrictly to him, and neuertheleſſe, two of them at leaſt, doe but hold by a bare and verie ſmall threed; As the third alſo would ſtand in the like caſe, but that beeing ſo neere and terryfying a neighbour of all ſides vnto the Pope, he holds him by the throat (as they ſay) being able to ſtarue him to death with all the Conſiſtorie, whenſoeuer he will but reſtraine the tranſportation of corne out of <hi>Sici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and other his dominions round about: whereby he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth more then he is commaunded (not perhaps more then hated, if they durſt ſhew it) and neuer giues their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt leaue to ſing any other ſong, but that which hee ſends him ready prickt from Madrid.</p>
            <p>Now then, if theſe men when they haue done al their vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt power, yea, in the ſtretching of their loue &amp; filial du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, enlarged kindnes beyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that which they can wel warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; yet can they aſſigne vnto their father the Pope, no more
<pb facs="tcp:3104:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
then a generall care of ſoules with a miniſteriall direction onely for order and execution of Canons ouer particular Churches; no power at all ouer the vniuerſall Church in groſſe, much leſſe ouer a generall Councell, much leſſe, or in the ſame degree, ouer the bodies of men by violence, or any temporall puniſhment, but by meere counſell &amp; perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on onely: And if not ſo much as ouer priuate bodies, leaſt of all ouer Kings and ciuill Princes, which rather they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and openly acknowledge to haue right and authoritie to commaund both Church and Church-men in ſome caſes; to which Princes all men, aſwell Eccleſiaſticall as Ciuill, must be moſt humble and faithfull ſubiects, as being (in ſo much as they be Lords of the territorie) eſtabliſhed by God, Protectors and Defendors of the Church, and of both Diuine and Naturall lawes with attribution of the materiall Sword to themſelues only, priuatiuely and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſiuely from all others within their owne dominions. What ſtop then any more, deere brethren, but that you ſhold gladly yeeld your naturall dutie and allegiance to your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall king, ſince ye are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to yeeld it euen <hi>to the frow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.18.</note> That you ſhould willingly giue him but that ſimple pawne of your loyaltie, your oath, the ſimplest that could euer be imagined vpon that great ſtraight and neceſsitie whereunto the State was brought by that portentuous miſchiefe, which did once ſo nearely and daungerouſly threaten kingdome and vs all, as you your ſelues haue bene most vndoubting eye-witneſſes? You ſhall not be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes neuertheleſſe, and you know how little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing beſides that, is required at your hands; your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences are no waies preſſed; your thoughts are moſt free, and your words (thank God for it and your gracious King)
<pb facs="tcp:3104:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
may freely expreſſe them. In ſo much that euerie day ſome of you (God forbid I ſhould ſay all) diſpute as peremptorily, ſpeake as odiouſly, decide as vnchriſtianly, inueigh as pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely againſt vs, and our Religion here, in the midſt of <hi>London,</hi> to our ſelues, and one to another to our owne faces, as thogh they were in the verie middle of <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Seuil</hi> very farre from the pittileſſe fiers of thoſe hot Countries, where they burn without remiſſion, not only ſuch as ſpeak the leaſt word, I doe not ſay against God (for they let them alone) but againſt the Pope, (for that is the greater ſinne) yea euen againſt thoſe they can by any meanes diſcouer to haue had, at any time, any thought, or bee able afterwards to haue it, against him. Onely all you may complaine of, is that yee haue not as free and as publike exer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſe, as we, of the rites of your Religion: And yet in ſome ſort haue yee it, by hooke and by crooke, or by a ſoueraigne tranſcendency of grace; ſo much haue euer all Magiſtrates of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion abhorred extreame execution of the lawes, but being forced thereunto by violent attempts. For ſhame therefore be contented; Enioy peaceably that liberty which you may buy ſo cheape; and rather loue the certaine quietneſſe of your preſent eſtate, then the incertitude of another, which ſure cannot be but troubleſome. Force not by an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural rebelliou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wilfulneſſe in ſo iuſt, in ſo lawfull a mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, your naturall and moſt gracious King to be moſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnwillingly, and with a great griefe to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s heart, more ſharp againſt you then the ſweet inclination and meeknes of his royall nature will beare.</p>
            <p>I conclude with an addition, to your further encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of ſome decrees d cided and ſet downe two hundred yeres agoe by the verie ſame <hi>Sorbonne</hi> againſt that falſe
<pb facs="tcp:3104:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
doctrine, and ſuch as ſeemed then to broach it a new, whom they neuer failed to condemne, and cauſed them publikely to aske pardon and make ſatisfaction, as Frier <hi>Iohn Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>razin, Iohn Tanquarell, Florentin Iacob, Thomas de Blanzy,</hi> and ſundrie others at ſundry times did; Which decrees yet now of late they haue cauſed againe to bee prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their owne Printer, <hi>Felix de Blanuile, in S. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors ſtreete in Paris,</hi> and bound together with this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent booke, with this title, <hi>Of the power and ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the Pope. Againſt the Sectaries of this age.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating once more the diffinition of the Church, as it is ſet downe in the title page of this booke, to point, as it were, with the finger that both ſprung together out of one &amp; the ſame fountaine: Whereby you may ſee how carefull they haue euer beene to daſh the young ones of Babilon againſt the right rocke of the truth.</p>
            <div type="decrees">
               <head>
                  <hi>The decrees are theſe, after a long rehearſall of the</hi> cauſe and ceremonies of <hi>Sarrazins</hi> recantation, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Rector of the Vniuerſity, and whole ſcores of Doctors there named one by one, as witneſſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> THat all powers of Eccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction, other then that of the Pope, are from Chriſt himſelfe in as much as concerneth primary inſtitution and collation; but from the Pope, and from the Church, for limitation and miniſteriall diſpenſation onely.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That thoſe powers are of diuine right and immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ordeined by God.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> That we finde in the Scripture that Chriſt hath foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:3104:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
his church, and expreſly ordained other powers, diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring from that of the Pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> That whenſoeuer any matters bee ordained in a Councel, the whole authoritie which giueth force to the decrees doth reſide not in the Pope onely and alone, but principally in the holy Ghost and the Catholike Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> That by the text of the Scripture and doctrine of the Apostles, wee ſee directly that authoritie of iuriſdiction was conferred vpon the Apoſtles and Diſciples when Chriſt did ſend them forth.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> That the power of Iuriſdiction of inferiour Prelates, either Biſhops or Curates, is immediatly from God, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the doctrine of the Goſpell and the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> That there is ſome power, that is the power of the Church, which of right and incertaine caſes can decree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> That any man liuing of whatſoeuer title, authority, dignity, or preeminence hee may be, euen though hee were a Pope, if onely he haue the vſe of reaſon, may commit Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
               <p>Finally, most heartily intreating you to take in the beſt part of this my louing zeale and feruent affection, I ceaſe; yet neuer ceaſing moſt deuoutly to pray ſtill both for your own good, for the kings ſeruice, for the peace of the land, &amp; generally for the ſeruice of God, that he will giue me grace I may tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> in your behalfe (ſince the caſe is not very much vnlike) that which he ſaith of the Iewes, Rom. <hi>9. I ſpeake the truth in Chriſt, I lie not, my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bearing me witneſſe in the holy Ghoſt, that I haue great heauineſſe and continuall ſorrow in my heart, for I would my ſelfe euen be ſeperate for my
<pb facs="tcp:3104:13"/>
brethren the</hi> [Romiſh Catholikes] <hi>to whome pertained the adoption, and the glorie, and the couenants, and the giuing of the law, and the ſeruice of God and the promiſes, of whome are the Fathers,</hi> and who hauing bequeathed or rather bequited them vnto vs, as the Sina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue had done vnto them, both remaine depriued thereof; Whereunto I pray God from the bottome of my heart to reſtore you all againe with vs, that ſo both Iewes and all Chriſtians, as naturall brethren after a long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord reconciled together vnder one God and father, one Lord and Elder Brother, in one Church and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may enioy together one eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in the heauenly Ieruſalem, which is the mother of vs all. Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:3104:14"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3104:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Argument of the whole Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe conſiſting of eighteene Sections.</head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ccleſiaſticall Iuriſdiction, chiefly and eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belongs to the Church, but to the Pope and o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther Biſhops miniſterially onely, as the power of ſeeing to the eye.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Chriſt immediatly and by himſelfe did giue the keyes or iuriſdiction vnto the hierachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call order, by the immediate and reall ſending forth of all the A<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtles and Diſciples.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The definition of the Church, by eſſentiall cauſes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> S. Peter is onely the diſpenſer &amp; miniſteriall head, but Chriſt the right abſolute Lord, eſſential &amp; head, founder &amp; foundation, of the Church. Wherefore all arguments drawne from the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall to the eſſential head, come ſhort &amp; are fallacious,<note n="*" place="margin">A dicto ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quid, ad dictum ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer.</note> as being inferred from that which is ſaid in ſome reſpect, to that which is affirmed ſimply.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> In the Church her ſtate muſt be diſtinguiſhed from her go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement; the ſtate being monarchicall, only to maintaine order and vnitie, and to the powerfull execution of the Canons; But the gouernment is Ariſtocraticall for wholeſome counſell, infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible prouidence and conſtitution of Canons: For the Church is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by Canons, not by abſolute power.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> The infallible power of decreeing &amp; making Canons, belongs to the whole Church, which is the very pillar &amp; ground of truth; not ſolely or onely to <hi>Peter:</hi> And that prooued by the practiſe of the whole Church.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3104:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> This place of the Goſpell expounded, <hi>Simon, Behold, Sathan hath deſired to wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow you as wheate; but I haue prayed for thee, that thy faith faile not &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> The frequent holding of Councels is abſolutely and ſimply ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to the better and more holy gouerning of the Church; and in what caſes the Buls and Decretals of Popes doe binde.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> How farre the fulneſſe of the Popes power may be extended; And in what caſe he may diſpenſe with the canons of Councels.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Though the Church haue but one eſſentiall head neuertheleſſe in regard of the exerciſe and execution of gouernment, ſhe is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently ruled by the Pope, and by the Ciuill Prince.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Whereas the Church hath neither territory, nor right of the Sword, from Chriſt (being onely ordained to a ſupernaturall and ſpirituall end) ſhee can determine of the meanes neceſſarie to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, onely by perſwaſion and direction, not by conſtraint or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting of temporall puniſhments.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> The ciuill Prince, as being Lord of the Common-wealth, and Country, is the Protector and Defendor both of the Diuine, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and Canonicall law, And to thoſe ends may both establiſh lawes, and exerciſe the ſword.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> The Ciuil Prince by the title of Protector of the Church, and defendor of the Canons, is the lawfull Iudge of all,<note n="*" place="margin">Appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones de abuſu.</note> 
               <hi>appeales for abuſe,</hi> as they are termed: And from thence haue the liberties of the Gallicane Church had their beginning.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Confutation of thoſe arguments which due attribute abſolute authoritie to Popes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> In a generall Councel the Pope is held to bee the head, ſo far forth as concernes preaching of the word, adminiſtration of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and execution of Canons; but not as touching direction and correctiue power ouer the whole Councell.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> This Canon expounded, <hi>No body muſt iudge the firſt See.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> The finall cauſe of the Church, which is euerla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ting life by a good gouernment, ſhowes euidently that <hi>Peter</hi> is by the Church, and for the Church; as the eye by man and for man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> What the meaning is, that the Church hath alſo indirect pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er in temporall things; And the anſweare to the contrarie argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:3104:15"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF Eccleſiaſticall and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke power.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a common Principle and of an vndoubted faith, that God &amp; Nature haue ſtill a more chiefe and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate regard to the whole, then to any part, neuer ſo noble, thereof. And for an example the power of Seing hath therefore bin giuen vnto man, that it might bee exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the eye, as mans inſtrument and miniſter to that purpoſe; for the eye ſubſiſteth both by man, and for man. The Schoole of Paris building vpon that moſt infallible ground, conformably to the opinion of all auncient Doctors of the Church, hath euer and moſt conſtantly taught, <hi>That Chriſt in the foundation of his Church hath more chiefly, immediatly and eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially giuen the keyes, or authoritie to the whole Church,
<pb facs="tcp:3104:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
then to Peter;</hi> Or (which comes al to one) <hi>That he hath giuen the keyes to the whole Church, miniſterially to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by one man:</hi> Seeing all Eccleſiaſticall power be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs properly, eſſentially and firſt, to the Church; but to the Pope, and other Biſhops inſtrumentally, and miniſterially, and onely ſo far forth as concernes the exerciſing, as the power of ſeeing to the eye: <hi>Let no body therefor glorie in men, for all things are yours</hi> (that is to ſay of the church) <hi>Whether it be Paul, or Apolos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, whether things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or to come; for all things are the Churches, and the Church Chriſts, and Chriſts Gods.</hi> 1. Cor. 3. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> For ſurely when it pleaſed our Sauiour <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19. to promiſe by words of future, the keyes to Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in the name of the whole Church, after this maner, <hi>I will giue thee the keyes of the kingdome of heauen, &amp;c.</hi> He did afterwards actually giue and deliuer them to the whole hierarchical order together, Firſt by a gene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rall commiſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. where he doth eſtabliſh the Church ſufficient in it ſelf, &amp; a chief Gouerneſſe <hi>Tell it vnto the Church;</hi> Secondly, by a reall ſending forth. <hi>Luc.</hi> 10.1. <hi>The Lord appointed other ſeauenty alſo, and ſent them two and two before him, into euerie citie &amp; place whither he himſelfe ſhold come.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.18.</note> Likewiſe when a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle before, or immediatly after the celebration of the Lords ſupper, he prayeth to his father for his Church in theſe words; <hi>As thou haſt ſent me into the world, ſo haue I ſent them into the world; and for their ſakes ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie I my ſelfe, that they alſo may bee ſanctified through the truth;</hi> And a verſe farther, <hi>That they all may bee one, as thou, O father, art in me, and I in thee; and may alſo be one
<pb facs="tcp:3104:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
in vs, that the world may beleeue thou haſt ſent me;</hi> And one verſe after, <hi>That they may be made perfect in one &amp;c</hi> By which words it appeares clerely, That Chriſt hath not deliuered the infallible power of the Keyes ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much vnto <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe and alone, as vnto the vnitie it ſelfe; as S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> and S. <hi>Auſten</hi> doe confirme, 24. quaeſt 1. can Quodcunque, can. Loquitur, can. Alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Moreouer, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.21. <hi>As my father ſent mee, ſo ſend I you, Receiue the holy Ghoſt, whoſoeuer: ſinnes you remit &amp;c.</hi> Seeing then, that true and reall miſſion is a conferring of iuriſdiction, by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15. <hi>And how ſhall they preach except they be ſent?</hi> And Chriſt immediatly, indiuidu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and iointly hath ſent all his Apoſtles and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples (which did repreſent the Epiſcopall and Prieſtly order) as he had beene ſent of his father, that is with a iuſt and ſpirituall authoritie, neceſſary for the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church; It followes, That the whole hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchical order, conſiſting of Biſhops &amp; Prieſts, doth deriue immediatly, yet in a proportion and ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, his power and iuriſdiction (that is his authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for the gouerning of the Church) from Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As in Fraunce, inferiour Iudges and Magiſtrates, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſubiect to Parliaments, deriue aſwell and as directly their authority from the King, as the Parliaments themſelues. <hi>For thoſe that bee are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God:</hi> And had neuer beene ſo ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned if there were not ſome ſubordination betweene thoſe magiſtrates, and the Eccleſiaſtical perſons. And finally the teſtimony of <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 20.28. <hi>Take heede therefore vnto your ſelues, and to all the flocke whereof the
<pb facs="tcp:3104:17"/>
holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops to gouerne the Church of God.</hi> Which doctrine S. <hi>Bernard lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Conſider, ad Eugen. cap.</hi> 10. dooth very cleerely make manifeſt. <q>Thou doſt deceiue thy ſelfe (ſaith hee) if thou thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt that as your Apoſtolicall power was ordained by God to be chiefeſt, ſo alſo to be alone. If thou be of that mind, thou art not of his mind who ſaid <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <hi>That there is no power but from God,</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that which followes, <hi>Whoſoeuer reſiſteth the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, reſisteth the ordinance of God,</hi> though it make principally for thee, neuertheleſſe not ſingularly. For the ſelfe ſame who ſaid, <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect vnto the higher powers,</hi> did not ſay vnto the higher power, as though they were but in one, but ſpeakes in the plurall as being in many. VVherefore thy power is not alone from God; There are ſome of the middle ſort yea &amp; ſome inferiour. And as they whome God hath ioyned muſt not be ſeuered, no more thoſe who are ſubiect to others muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to them. Thou doſt forme a monſter, if re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouing a finger from the hand, thou wilt haue it hang at the head, ſuperiour to the hand, col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laterall to the arme: So is it if in the bodie of the Church, thou placeſt the members other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then he hath diſpoſed them,<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4 11</note> 
                  <hi>who hath ſet ſome in the Church to bee Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſts, ſome Paſtours and Teachers, for the perfit vnion of the Saints in the worke of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery, and edification of the body of Chriſt.</hi>
               </q> Let the Godly rather looke the whole chapter.</p>
            <p>But if any happen to obiect that this power which
<pb facs="tcp:3104:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Chriſt by an immediate miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did transfer to his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, doth not ſo much concern the authority of the outward, as of the inward Court. The anſwere is, that vniuerſally al the ancient fathers of the Church haue abſolutly expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded it of whatſoeuer power neceſſary to rule the Church, as wel in the inward, as in the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Court; And that we are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a great deale more to giue credit to their ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d deciſions, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſubtle diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of ſome Noualiſts, forged at pleaſure, more eaſily to maintaine &amp; enlarge their liberties, &amp; extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary miſſions, euen to the ouerthrow of common right. Beſides, That the ſum of the whole outward iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction reaches no farther then to the power of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which afterwards Sect. 6 ſhalbe clearely proued to haue immediatly bin deliuered vp by Chriſt to the Church. Yet perhaps they wil pretend, that this power of iuriſdiction was indeed ordained &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferred at firſt by Chriſt to the whole Church, but with ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that it ſhold be afterwards co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to other Biſhops, by the Popes, as ſucceſſors to S. <hi>Peter:</hi> And therfore now al authoritie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth &amp; is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued only from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. But thus ſtop you their mouth, That it is moſt appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by the practiſe of the primitiue Church, &amp; by the holy cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, that al collatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices (as they are now called,) haue bin 1400. yeares together made by a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> right, that is, by holy electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The reaſon is, becauſe al principality, ſo far as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pulſiue power, depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of men, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s both diuine &amp; natural law do confirme; againſt which neither length of time, priuiledge of places, nor digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of perſons, can euer preſcribe. Which grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d being
<pb facs="tcp:3104:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
thus layed and ſetled, of neceſſitie theſe eight next enſuing principles muſt directly follow.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> The firſt ſhall vnfold the definition of the Church, Which is a Monarchicall gouernment ordained to a ſupernaturall and ſpirituall end, tempered with an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtocraticall order (which is the beſt of all, and moſt conformable to nature) by the greateſt Paſtor of ſoules, Ieſus Chriſt our Lord; Who is the only King, Monarch, abſolute Lord, Founder, foundation and eſſentiall head of the Church, hauing an abſolute and purely monarchical command ouer her: And who, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though by his omnipotencie, and infinite power, hee might haue ſaued all mankind without the ſcandall of the Croſſe, neuertheleſſe to confound and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the power, pride, arrogancie and wiſedome of the world, And teach his Miniſters to thinke moſt lowly of themſelues, <hi>Yet was pleaſed by the fooliſhneſſe of preaching to ſaue them that beleeue, that no fleſh ſhould glory in his preſence, Cor.</hi> 1.25.29. Whereof wee will treate Section. 11. From whence we doe alſo inferre, this Article of faith [I beleeue one holy Catholike Church] to bee of an euerlaſting veritie, ſeeing as long as the Euangelicall Law doth ſtand, Chriſt cannot make any diuorce from the Church, his Spouſe. Which cannot properly bee ſaid of her Simbolicall and Miniſteriall head, the Pope; Whome wee often ſee to bee abſent and preſent, for a time at leaſt, without deſtruction of the Church, for who is ignorant that the Apoſtolike Sea hath ſometimes three, ſometimes ſeuen yeares<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> beene vacant? So that the Commaundement of
<pb facs="tcp:3104:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
hauing a Pope is affirmatiue, and not negatiue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> The ſecond principle teacheth, That Saint <hi>Peter</hi> is only the diſpenſer and Miniſteriall head, not the Lord, Founder or foundation of the Church; Titles which belong indeede vnto one Chriſt alone, and only the eſſentiall head; by whome, and for whome the Church ſubſiſteth: for which cauſe alſo hee ſpeakes thus to <hi>Peter,, Matthew</hi> 16.18. <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter <hi>and vpon this rocke will I build my Church, and the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it.</hi> Wherein is to bee noted that hee doth not ſay thy Church, or the gates of Hell ſhall not preuaile againſt thee; likewiſe Iohn 21.15. <hi>Feede my Lambes, Feede my Sheepe,</hi> hee doth not ſay thy Sheepe, or thy Lambes: And that purpoſely, to ſhew that Eccleſiaſticall men are called to a meere and ſimple diſpenſation or adminiſtration, not to any temporall Dominion or Gouernment meerely and abſolute Monarchicall. <hi>The Kinges of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions raigne ouer them, but with you it ſhall not bee ſo Luc.</hi> 22.25. and 1. Peter 5.2. <hi>Feed the flock which depends vpon you, caring for it, not by conſtraint, but willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not as Lords of the flocke, but that yee may bee a good example to them.</hi> Which places of the Scripture <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard ad Eugen.</hi> lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cap. 5. doth expound after this ſort. <hi>Goe then thou alſo, and vſurpe, if thou dare, either an Apoſtleſhip being a Lord, or a Lordſhip being Apoſtolicall. Thou art plainely forbidden both, and if thou wouldſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe both together, thou ſhalt looſe both This is the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolical forme, Dominion is forbidden, miniſtration is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded and commended by the example of the law-giuer,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3104:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.27.</note>
               <hi>I am in the midſt of you as one that miniſtreth &amp;c.</hi> By which both Saint <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Bernard</hi> doe ſet before our eyes a patterne of ariſtocraticall gouernment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which ſhall bee more largely deſcribed afterwards Sect. 5. 6. and 8. I am not ignorant that our Noue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, better to defend their priuiledges, doe maintaine that by theſe words, <hi>Feed my ſheep,</hi> Chriſt hath giuen the whole Eccleſiaſtical iuriſdiction, ſolely to <hi>Peter</hi> alone, to diſtribute it afterwards at his pleaſure to whom he would. But thoſe idle pretences are ſo plainely and manifeſtly confuted by the Oracles of holy Scripture, by the teſtimony of all auncient Fathers, and by the whole practiſe of the primitiue Church, that it is a great wonder how they dare forge ſuch abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. For indeed this ſpeech of our Lord, <hi>Feed my ſheep &amp;c.</hi> doth confer vpon S. <hi>Peter,</hi> as a miniſteriall head a prime and ful authoritie of adminiſtring, or executing the diuine, naturall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and canonicall law, according to the rules of ariſtocraticall moderation: Vpon which point looke Sect. 9. Which grounds being thus laid, al thoſe and other like arguments remain very eaſily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That <hi>Petrus</hi> is <hi>Petra,</hi> the foundation &amp; head of the Church, and therefore without him the Church falleth: Or that as a body being without a head, a ſtreame without a ſpring, a beame without a Sunne, a branch without a ſtock, an arme of a tree cut from his body, periſheth and withereth; no more can the Church ſubſiſt without a Pope. As though the Pope were the primary, and not the ſecondary, the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, and not the miniſteriall, Head of the Church. Whence followes that the commandement of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:3104:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
a Pope binds,<note n="*" place="margin">Ad ſemper non pro ſemper, <hi>As Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſpeake.</hi>
               </note> for euer, but not at all times.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="V"/> The third principle makes a diſtinction betweene the State of the Church and her gouernment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the State indeed is monarchicall, as wel to maintaine vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie &amp; order, as to execute the Canons, which executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is proper enough to the Pope, as to a miniſteriall head: But the gouernment is Ariſtocraticall, for found prouidence, effectuall counſell, and decreeing of thoſe Canons; for which cauſe wee ſayd Sect. 1. That the keyes were giuen to the whole Church to bee vſed by one man. For God hath ordained his Church, his Spouſe, to be gouerned by Canon or counſel, that the Pope and other Biſhops might not bee able to decree any thing of moment of their own head, or by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of ſome oligarchicall Councell, that is to ſay of few; but that they ſhould ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſſemble &amp; craue the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of an ariſtocratical Councel of the church. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doe we read that it was ordained by the auncient Fathers, that euerie yeare two prouinciall Councels ſhold be aſſembled. For look what proportion there is betwixt a generall Councel and the Pope, the ſame is alſo betweene particular Sinods &amp; their Biſhops. For particular Churches likewiſe muſt bee gouerned by their own Biſhops, with the rule of Canons, not with abſolute power. Furthermore we hold, the right and naturall Senate or Counſell of the Church, inſtructed by our Lord, to be not only the aſſembly of all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, but of all Prieſts hauing charge of ſoules; Of the which the former ſucceede the Apoſtles, the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſeuenty Diſciples. Diſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. Can. <hi>Charepiſcopi;</hi> ibid. Quaeſt. 1. Can. <hi>Eccleſia;</hi> and Diſt. 23. Can. <hi>Presbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3104:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
For the Prieſts indeede in times paſt did go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Church in common, as Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> doct. wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes. Can. <hi>Legimus.</hi> Diſt. 93.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VI"/> The fourth principle is, That the infallible power of decreeing and making Canon, is in the power of the whole Church, or of a generall Councell repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting the ſame: Wherein principally conſiſteth the nature of ariſtrocraticall gouernment, and is moſt clearely demonſtrated, partly by diuine, partly by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall light. For indeede many eies can ſee farther and clearer then one alone, neither is it giuen either from God or nature to any one alone to bee wiſe, leaſt hee ſhould glo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie in himſelfe. Moreouer. <hi>The body (of the Church) is not one member only, but manie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> If the whole bodie were an eye, where were the hearing</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Cor. 12.24.17. <hi>And the ſpirits of the Prophets are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Prophets;</hi> that is to the Church. 1. Cor. 14 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>There is but one Biſhopricke, whereof a part is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um,</hi> that is wholy, <hi>by euery one.</hi> 24. Quaeſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tur.</hi> Wherefore it is neceſſarie that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncernes all, ſhould be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> alſo approued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Since euery high Prieſt is taken from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpaſſed with infirmitie. Heb.</hi> 5.1.2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and bee deceiued, except hee req<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Church, which is the pillar &amp; groun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>refore when Chriſt was readie t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee doth promiſe the ſpirit of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urch, not vnto on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and only <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>And I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> pray the Father, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter, that hee may abide with you for euer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſpirit of truth.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.
<pb facs="tcp:3104:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> doth eſtabliſh his Church ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient in it ſelfe, and a chiefe Commandreſſe, by the erecting of an infalible Court, whiles hee doth ſo in theſe following words inſtruct Saint <hi>Pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> deſirous to know how many times he ſhould forgiue his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offending. <hi>If thy brother trespaſſe againſt thee, goe and proue him betweene thee and himſelf, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. And if hee refuſe to heare the Church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnto thee as an H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>then man and a Publican. Verily I ſay vnto you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> yee bind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhalb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in heauen &amp;c. Againe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> if two of you ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> agree in earth vpon any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing whatſoeuer they ſhall deſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it ſhall bee giuen: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> which is in heauen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For where two or three are ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>red together in my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, there am I in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> middeſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> By which ſpeech wee learne that Chriſt hath grant, the power of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication immediatly to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which is ſigni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hare by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Church; for as the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of ten dot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eminently and cauſelty com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>umb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> likewiſe doth this former ſpeech, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Church,</hi> eminently I ſay, and cauſally compre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> power <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> euery ſupe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with any iuriſdiction, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Pope, or a generall Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſupreame and infallible co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t-co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of authoritie all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> reſolue. And this is manifest, becauſe as ſoone as the Lord had vttered this ſpeech in the ſingular, <hi>Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Church,</hi> hee doth immediatly adde in the plurall, <hi>Verily I ſay vnto you, whatſoeuer yee ſhall ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n earth, &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3104:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Wherby it manifeſtly appeares that the Church is ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly &amp; properly for man; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en gathered together, not for any one man alone. Therefore with the ſame c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rent of ſpeech, Chriſt giues alſo to the Church the power to aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble it ſelfe in a Councel, and there infalibly to decree; <hi>Again I ſay vnto you, If two of you ſhall agree together on earth &amp;c. for where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midſt of them.</hi> Neither is it to be paſt in ſilence that Chriſt in this text doth denote the Ariſtocratical Councell eſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bliſhed by his owne diuine law, not the oligarchicall, afterwards inſtituted by men; And that hee hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely expreſſed a certaine number, and that the leaſt of numbers, for an vncertaine, to take away from contentious men all occaſion of ſhifting &amp; auoiding; and to ſhew that for a luſt gouerning of the Church, the conſent &amp; agreement of two or three at the leaſt is required, not of the Pope ſolely and alone. Truely to what ſide ſoeuer the aduerſaries will turne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they muſt needs confeſſe that theſe words, <hi>for where two or three are gathered together in my name,</hi> doe neceſſarily exclude that abſolute and infallible autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rity of the Pope alone, and do proue that the Church cannot bee bound againſt her will, nor without her conſent &amp; aduice required, which euery way agreeth with the natural law, &amp; is ſufficiently co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed by the practiſe of the Ancient Church. For the Councell of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the conſent &amp; voices of al the Apoſtles and Prieſts concludes with this ſtile. Act. 15.28. <hi>It ſee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med good to the holy ghoſt and to vs.</hi> Moreouer the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Africane Church, amongſt whome was
<pb facs="tcp:3104:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> writ vnto Pope <hi>Celeſtin</hi> 1. in theſe words. <hi>That it is not credible that God doth inſpire the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtice of examination into any one man, and deny it to an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> number of men lawfully gathered together is a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> The opinion alſo of Pope <hi>Zozimus</hi> make for the confirmation of this doctrine, when writing to the Biſhops of France hee confeſſeth himſelfe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainely to bee infe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>our to the Councell, and the au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>horitie of the Apoſtolicall Sea not able to derogat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the holy decrees of Councells, 25 Quaeſt. 1. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>To decree or change any thing againſt the decrees of the fathers, no not the very authoritie of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is able to doe it. Holy antiquitie, liues with v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, vnſhaken in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> foundation, whereunto the decrees of the fathers ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ordained all reuerence.</hi> To this may well bee added the anſwere of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the great, <hi>Who confeſſeth that he reuerenceth the foure generall Councells, euen as the foure bookes of the holy Goſpell; for being conſtituted with vniuerſall conſent whoſoeuer preſumes to looſe that which they bind, or to bind that which they looſe, doth but deſtroy himſelfe and not them</hi> Diſt. 15. Can. <hi>Sicut Sancti Euangelij.</hi> And true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if one will, neuer ſo little, peruſe the acts of gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councells, he ſhall eaſily perceiue, that the Pope doth not ſolely and himſelfe alone make decrees of the Catholike faith in thoſe generall Synods, but doth inferre and conclude them by the induction and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vniuerſally taken of all particular Churches. Which indeede is the moſt certaine and moſt euident proofe of an Ariſtocraticall gouernment, and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed. Can. <hi>Maiores.</hi> 24. Quaeſt. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VII"/> But if ſome perhaps will yet argue that Chriſt did
<pb facs="tcp:3104:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
pray for <hi>Peter.</hi> 22. Luc. 32. <hi>that his faith ſhould not faile, and commanded him to confirme his brethren.</hi> Wee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the firſt part, that this promiſe of Chriſt according to the litterall ſence of the Scripture, doth not extend farther then the time of the Lords paſſion; Wherein the ſcandall of the Croſſe was moſt furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to rage againſt all the diſciples, and principally againſt <hi>Peter,</hi> who thrice denied his Maſter. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Lord ſpeakes after this manner to them all. Mat. 26.31. <hi>All yee ſhall bee offended in me this night, for it is written, I will ſmite the Shepheard, and the ſheepe of the flocke ſhalbe ſcattered. But Peter anſwering ſayd vnto him, Though all men ſhould be offended in thee, yet will I neuer be offended; Ieſus ſaid vnto him, verily I ſay vnto thee, that this night before the Cock crow thou ſhalt denie mee thrice.</hi> Moreouer, Luc. 22.31. <hi>Simon, beholde, Sathan hath deſired you, to winnow you as wheate, but I haue praied for thee, that thy faith faile not, wherefore when thou art conuerted, ſtrengthen thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> Wherein is principally to be noted that Chriſt did not ſay to <hi>Peter,</hi> I haue prayed for thee that thou maiſt neuer erre, or be ſubiect to be deceiued; But on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly I haue prayed for thee, that thy faith faile not: And that <hi>Peter</hi> indeede did erre, yet his faith neuer failed him, in regard of the habite, but only of the act, for he did only denie the Lord with his mouth, not with his heart. To the ſecond point, who will aduiſedly examine that which preceedes and followes this text, euen at the firſt ſight hee ſhall find that after Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was out of that dangerous ſtaggering of his trebble deniall, and come againe to his right ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb facs="tcp:3104:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
as from a moſt deepe and dead ſleepe, hee was farre more able both to ſettle and ſtay his wauering fellowes, and to call againe to the Church all his ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered brethren, that there together they might expect the reſurrection of the Lord. Therefore that argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theirs is fallacious, being inferred <hi>a dicto ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum quid, ad dictum ſimplicitèr,</hi> from that which is ſaid in ſome reſpect, to that which is affirmed ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. For that priuiledge did reach no farther then Saint <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe and alone, becauſe of the immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent ſcandall of the Croſſe. And ſure if the Pope alone and not the Church, iointly taken, be infalible, It followes that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſinned moſt greeuouſly, Galat. 2.11. telling vs ſo plainly that therefore Saint <hi>Peter was reprehenſible, becauſe hee went not the right way to the truth of the Goſpell;</hi> Which words are moſt worthy to be noted. Beſides that, this repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, as the Pariſian Chauncelor well obſerueth, is equiualent to an appeale to a Councell. For if Saint <hi>Peter</hi> had at that time reſiſted Saint <hi>Paul</hi> iuſtly reprouing him, no doubt but the Church, gathering herſelfe together in a Councell, would haue taken vp the difference betwixt them, as a little before ſhe had decided the controuerſie about the obſeruation of le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall Ceremonies. Act. 15.1. In this place, as for a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle acceſſorie and enlarging of fauour, wee may adde that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> by the right interpretation of the Scripture and Canons, may ſtrengthen in the faith particular perſons, or a Church, which are gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray; and in that ſence Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> in an Epiſtle to Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi> doth require of him leaue to ſay, or
<pb facs="tcp:3104:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
not ſay <hi>Hypoſtaſes</hi> in the plurall number, which is as much as the interpretation of the Nicene Creede; <hi>I deſire,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>from a Paſtor the aſsiſtance hee owes to a ſheepe; Conſider of it according to your iudgement, I ſhall not feare to ſay three Hypoſtaſes, if if you bid me:</hi> And the ſame hath euer beene the regard of <hi>Theodoret,</hi> and of all the reſt, when at any time they haue had their refuge to the holy Apoſtolicall Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="VIII"/> The firſt principle ſhewes, That often celebration of Councells is abſolutely and ſimply neceſſarie, for the better and more holy gouerning of the Church, for as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith in his Politikes, It is farre more expedient to be ruled by lawes, then by the abſolute power of any whoſoeuer. For lawes indeede are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of God, and are not poſſeſſed either with loue or hatred, or any other humane paſſion. Whence it comes that you find ſo ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe Phraſes in the Actes of the Councells, <hi>To doe any thing beſides the Canon, without the Canon, againſt the Canon, according to the Canon.</hi> By which ſtile is ſhewed that the Church muſt bee directed by Canon, and that in auncient times nothing was decreed without a Councel, and Ariſtocraticall moderation. Hence alſo is it that we reade how the Biſhops of France wrote vnto Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> that the Bulls and Decretalls of Popes doe no way bind vnleſſe they agree with the diſcipline of Canons, and Councells formerly receiued and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued. Can. <hi>Si Romanorum</hi> Diſt. 9. To which alſo ought to bee referred the Canon <hi>Omnia.</hi> Quaeſt. 1. Whereupon looke <hi>Flodoardus</hi> lib. 3. cap. 21. pag. 231. Who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Father <hi>Sirmond</hi> a Ieſuite hath euen of late pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed,
<pb facs="tcp:3104:23"/>
ſince indeede the Pope which is but the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriall head cannot bind the vniuerſall Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out calling her, without hearing her, and without ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her counſell and conſent. <hi>For then are the lawes eſtabliſhed when they are publiſhed, and then confirmed, when approued by the practiſe of thoſe that liue vnder them.</hi> As <hi>Auſten</hi> witneſſeth, Diſt. 4. Can. <hi>In iſtis</hi> And therein ſtands principally the libertie of the Catholike Church, or the Ariſtocraticall gouernment, and is the ſpeedieſt and gentleſt meanes to vnite and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent Schiſmes againe. Vpon the ground of which principle <hi>Hinemarus</hi> Archbiſhop of Rhemes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth to another <hi>Hinemarus</hi> Biſhop of Laon, his Nephew, That the decretall Epiſtles of Popes repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be ſet forth before the Councell of Nice are but of ſmall credit, becauſe they agreed not with the holy Canons. Whereupon looke likewiſe <hi>Flodoard</hi> lib. 3. cap. 22. fol. 243 <hi>verſo &amp;c.</hi> 244. <hi>recto.</hi> And from thence alſo wee may plainely learne what law our French Predeceſſors haue euer vſed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IX"/> The ſixt principle defines the fulneſſe of the Popes
authoritie. Firſt, towards the particular Churches diſperſed through the world, but no manner of way towards the whole Church gathered together in a Councell; Secondly, in the matter of execution, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation, and diſpenſation; but no wayes to the conſtitution of Canons, vnleſſe either by himſelfe, or by his Legats hee preſide in the Councell, and gather the voyces and conſent of all the Fathers as we haue proued Sect. 6. But the Pope may diſpenſe with the decrees of Councells in ſuch a caſe only as the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell
<pb facs="tcp:3104:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
it ſelfe might diſpence, were it aſſembled; And that is confirmed by the opinion of Pope <hi>Zozi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> which wee haue commended Sect. 6. As alſo of <hi>Leo</hi> 7. Can. <hi>Priuilegio. Diſpenſation,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>is comit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs, and it ſhall be laid to our charge, if the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons decreed by the fathers be violated, either with our conſent or careleſneſſe.</hi> Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> lib. 3. <hi>ad Eugen.</hi> cap. 10. <hi>What? ſaiſt thou, doeſt thou forbid vs to diſpenſe? No, but to diſsipate. I am not ſo ignorant that I doe not know that you are placed to be diſpenſers, but to edification, not to deſtruction. Finally it is required at the hands of diſpenſers that they bee found faithfull. Where neceſsitie vrgeth diſpenſation is excuſable; when vtilitie inciteth it is commended; common vtilitie, I ſay, not priuate.</hi> So that in theſe two points which wee haue treated of in this diſcourſe, all the Monarchicall eſtate of the Church, or the fulneſſe of the Popes authoritie, doth princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally conſiſt; not in an abſolute power, which many of our Noualiſts now, againſt both diuine and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall law, ſtriue to intrude into the Church. Certainly eight hundred yeares agoe and aboue, that is euen be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tranſlation of the Roman Empire to our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Popes did but call them ſelues maintainers and executors of the Canons. Finally by tract of time, when all Chriſtendome lay altogether buried in the logs of darknes and ignorance, they gathered to themſelues abſolute authority to decree of all things; Eſpecially ſince the time of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth, whole life, largely written by <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> thoſe that are curious of the truth of the Storie may read: And they ſhall further obſerue that the Pope regular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:3104:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and ordinarily hath the power to call the generall Councells, in ſo much as hee hath power ouer the particular Churches diſperſed ouer the face of the whole Earth. Now the ſumme of all this diſputation is, that from the monarchicall State of the Church, all vnitie and order, with a powerfull execution of the Canons doe proceede. But from the Ariſtocraticall gouernment proceedeth moſt holy counſell, infa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lible prouidence, and finall deciſion; Whereby the Chriſtian Common-wealth is gouerned to a perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall edification, not deſtruction.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="X"/> The ſeuenth principle teacheth vs, That the Church taken either for the whole companie of the faithfull, or for the Chriſtian Common-wealth, is contented with her ſole only head, and eſſentiall foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, Neuertheleſſe in the matter of exerciſe and execution of gouernment in this Chriſtian Common-wealth, ſhee is differently ruled by two diuers perſons, that is by the Pope, and the Ciuill Prince, Can. <hi>Duo ſunt</hi> Diſt. 96 and Can <hi>Princi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes,</hi> 25 Quaeſt. 5. Conformably to the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the Lord Mat. 22.21. <hi>Giue vnto</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things which are</hi> Caeſars, <hi>and to God thoſe that are Gods.</hi> For by this, as by a mutuall band of loue and obliga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, the Lord was pleaſed to knit together the Church &amp; the Ciuill power; that Princes &amp; Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhould not quarrell one againſt another. Which wholeſome diſtinction, whoſoeuer they be that know not, or doe diſſemble, or confound, doe runne vpon huge and moſt perilous rockes, and make Church men, as factious and dangerous perſons, ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted
<pb facs="tcp:3104:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
to the Ciuill Princes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XI"/> But for our 8 principle, Let vs enter a little further in this point: for ſince the Euangelicall law hath no other end but euerlaſting life, and the ſoule of man for his matter and naturall ſubiect; It ought wholly to apply it ſelfe about the direction of the inward motions of the conſcience, but no wayes in any out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward force or violence; And therefore iudgeth only of meanes neceſſarie to ſaluation, conformably to the eſſential &amp; ſpiritual cauſes of Chriſtian religion; that is perſuaſiuely only, and directiuely, in preaching of the word, adminiſtration of Sacraments, and, if need require, excluſion of Communion with the Church by vertue of cenſures, the ſpirituall armes of the Church; which in ancient times it was a great crime to exerciſe without mature counſell and Ariſtocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical moderation of the Prieſtly order, as we haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Sect. 5. And ſo much the nature of Ariſtocrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call gouernment did require, and euer ſince that hath beene diſcontinued, the learned know what diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline hath enſued. Now this doctrine is grounded, partly vpon the definition of the Church deliuered, Sect. 3. partly vpon many ſtrong and euident Oracles of the Scripture. Doth not our Lord diſtinctly auerre to Pilate, Iohn 18.36. that <hi>his Kingdome is not of this world?</hi> And Luc. 9.58. <hi>The foxes haue holes, and the birds of heauen neſts, but the ſonne of man hath not whereon to lay his head?</hi> As though hee would ſay, That the Church, as from God, hath neither territorie, nor vſe of ſword, of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or of any corporall puniſhment: for the ſoule,
<pb facs="tcp:3104:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
which is the only and proper ſubiect of Euangelicall law, is only moued by an inward, not by an outward beginning: but the right of the materiall ſword ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily followeth the territorie, as they effect the cauſe. Hence was it that the Lord did anſwer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to one of the people that deſired him to bid his brother to diuide with him their fathers inheritance, Luc. 12.14. <hi>Man, who made me a Iudge, or a diuider ouer you?</hi> As though hee had ſaid, That the Church which hath for her ſubiect the ſoules of men, not earthly Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, ought not to iudge of earthly inheritances and poſſeſſions. For <hi>walking in the fleſh, yet doe wee not warre after the fleſh; for the weapons of our warfare are not carnall, but mightie through God to caſt downe holds, caſting downe the imaginations and euery high thing that is exalted against the knowledge of God, and bringing into captiuitie euery thought to the obedience of Chriſt.</hi> 2 Cor. 10.3. Where is to be noted, that by the materiall ſword the bodies may bee compelled, yea killed, but by no ſuch meanes the thoughts to be cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuated to the obedience of Chriſt; for that is only effected by the wholeſome food of the Word and Sacraments. And to this the witneſſe of Paul, Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip. 3.20. <hi>Our</hi> Politeuma, <hi>that is Chriſtian gouernment, is wholly in heauen, from whence wee looke for the Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi> And ſo indeede would our Lord haue it, that Church men ſhould not meddle in violent and temporall matters. <q>Will you haue alſo the teſtimonie of Saint <hi>Bernard?</hi> They ſhall neuer ſhew, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> when euer any of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles hath ſitten as a Iudge of men, diuider of
<pb facs="tcp:3104:26"/>
bounds, or diſtributer of grounds. Finally I reade that the Apoſtles did ſtand before the Iudges to bee iudged, but not that they did ſit iudging others. Therefore your power reaches no further then to ſinnes, not to poſſeſſions; becauſe for thoſe, not for theſe, you did receiue the keyes of the Kingdome of heauen, to ſhut out offendors only, not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſors. I pray thee, which power and dignitie doſt thou eſteeme greater, to remit ſinnes, or to diuide poſſeſſions? But there is no compariſon therein. Theſe earthly and inferior things haue their iudges by themſelues, the Kings and Princes of the earth, Why doe yee inuade other mens liberties?</q> Againſt thoſe diuine oracles, though more cleare then noone-light, two obiections principally are made; The firſt, that <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> his wife were puniſhed with death by Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> becauſe of their lie to the holy Ghoſt Act. 5. The ſecond, that the Apoſtle ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to teach Chriſtians, whileſt they liued vnder Heathen Princes and Magiſtrates, that they might chooſe Iudges among themſelues in their ciuill buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, 1. Cor. 6.4. <hi>If then yee haue iudgements of things pertaining to this life, ſet them vp which are leaſt eſteemed in the Church.</hi> We anſwere to the firſt that ſuch a great action of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was altogether miraculous, extraordinarie and wholly by the inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the holy Ghoſt; And therefore not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliable to ordinarie right, nor can no more be drawne into argument in either, then theſe words, <hi>Ierem.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Behold this day haue I ſet thee ouer Nations and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, to plucke vp, to roote out, to deſtroy and to thre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3104:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
downe;</hi> Or that place of the two ſwords. Luc. 22.38. ſeeing both places muſt be vnderſtood Allegorically and ſpiritually, but that from an Allegoricall and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall ſence there can no forcible argument bee drawne, the very children know it. Neither is there any reaſon that the authoritie of Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſhould breed any ſcruple in any mans minde, lib. 4. cap. 4 <hi>ad Eugen.</hi> 
               <q>Put vp thy ſword into thy ſheath; The ſword therefore is alſo thine, to bee perhaps vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheathed at thy direction, though not with thine owne hand. For both ſpirituall and materiall ſwords belong to the Church; But the one to be drawne for the Church, and the other by the Church. That by the hand of the Prieſt; this, of the Souldior, though indeede by the Prieſts apointment, but by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors commaundement.</q> For indeede theſe words doe but ſhew, That the Church hath right to giue the ſigne, that is to ſay, to teach and perſwade when the Ciuill Prince ought to draw his ſword for the glorie of God. Whereof wee will ſpeake in the Section following. And truly when Church-men did excell in holineſſe of life, Chriſtian Princes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue all ſuſpition of iniuſtice from their conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and enterpriſes, did vſe, and that very iuſtly, the counſell of Clergy-men both in peace and in warre. But as iuſtly againe haue they left to take it, ſince Churchmen gaue occaſion to ſuſpect that they affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted that temporall Monarchie, whereof <hi>Eugubinus, Bozius, Garrerius</hi> and the very Cardinalls <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Baronius</hi> haue written moſt laborious bookes. Which opinion, euen though it were true, yet wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb facs="tcp:3104:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
and reaſon, ſhould haue taught thoſe authors, at leaſt in thoſe moſt vnlucky dayes, to abſtaine from ſuch manner of writing. The ſecond argument de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues <hi>ab ignoratione Elenshi, through vnskilfulneſſe of arguing;</hi> for howbeit thoſe teſtimonies of holy Scripture, aboue commended, conclude manifeſtly, that the Church by diuine right hath neither territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, right of ſword, nor contentious Court: yet they doe not denie but by humane right and graunt of Princes, ſhee may very well haue it. Now for this place in queſtion, the Apoſtle doth not ſpeake of the diuine right, but of the humane and arbitrarie right, as when by a mutuall agreement of the parties, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate arbiters are choſen friendly to decide differences and controuerſies, without troubleſome going to law. For euery man will eaſily obſerue thus much, that ſhall reade the 6. chap. of the 1. to the Corint. conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratly and without all preiudice, only bringing with him a deſire of the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XII"/> Now let vs paſſe to the ciuill power. Truly ſince the ciuill Prince is the Lord of the Common-wealth and Countrie, protector and defendor of the diuine, naturall and canonicall law, And to that end doth beare the ſword; It is he alone that hath the power of conſtraining and reſtraining, by inflicting corporall puniſhment. Wherefore, for the good of the Church and execution of Eccleſiaſticall Canons, he may make lawes, and inroll them among his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, Records &amp; Charters, as we find that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, <hi>Conſtantine, Theodoſius, Iuſtinian, Charles</hi> the great, Saint <hi>Lewis, Charles</hi> 7. <hi>Francis</hi> 1. and others of
<pb facs="tcp:3104:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
our Kings haue done. Whereupon Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> Epiſt. 48. <hi>ad Vincent. The Kings of the earth ought to ſerue Chriſt, euen making lawes for Chriſt, according to the admonition of</hi> Dauid, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 2.10. <hi>Be yee wiſe now therefore yee Kings, be learned yee Iudges of the earth, ſerue the Lord in feare. Euſebius</hi> likewiſe cap 24 lib. 4 of the life of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, rehearſeth that that Noble Emperour was wont thus to ſpeake vnto his Biſhops; <hi>Yee are eſtabliſhed Biſhops by God, within the Church, and I a Biſhop without.</hi> As if hee would ſay, that it is the dutie of Chriſtian Princes, by vertue of their owne offi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o make ordinances for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the diuine, naturall and Canonicall law; and if occaſion require, draw the ſword: yet keeping ſtill the moderation of the parable of the tares Mat. 13.30. That is to ſay, without breach of the publike peace. And the ſame is confirmed by the ſame Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> Epiſt. <hi>ad Vincent.</hi> euen now named. All which things being well conceiued, It is eaſie to perceiue both in what ſence <hi>Optatus Mileuitanus</hi> affirmeth, That the Church is within the Common-wealth, that is, as it were vpon another mans ground, Territory, and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion; And alſo whether Chriſtian Princes did in times paſt aſſemble the Councells of Nice, Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinople, Epheſus, Chalcedon, and other generall Synods, rightfully or wrongfully: for that indeede concernes the execution of the diuine, naturall and Canonicall law.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XIII"/> Here for a corrollary and ſhort addition wee will adde one word more, which is, That the naturall li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Catholike Church, or the common
<pb facs="tcp:3104:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
right giuen her by God and Nature, are clearely ſtrengthned in theſe eight grounds and principles, ſo that none can except againſt them, but withall hee muſt needs infringe the whole diuine, naturall and canonicall law. And this, looke how often it hath hapned, ſo often hath it giuen iuſt occaſion to our Frenchmen to appeale from it as from an abuſe; Of which appeales the Prince and Ciuill Magiſtrate, as being the protector of the Church, and defendor of the Canons, hath the ſupreame moderation. For hee iudgeth of the abuſe only, and that belongs to the execution of the caſe. And inde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> that manner of proceeding among our French hath cauſed the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the liberties of the Gallicane Church, as they are commonly termed. As alſo I heare that Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards &amp; other chriſtian nations, when any thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the Court of Rome, which is againſt their cuſtomes and orders, are wont to labor by intreatie that it might not be put in execution. Whence it appeares that in the matter it ſelfe they agree with vs, but diſagree only in the forme and manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="confutation">
            <pb facs="tcp:3104:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Confutation of the <hi>contrarie opinion.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XIIII"/> THoſe that maintaine the contrarie opinion, that is the Popes abſolute power, Firſt doe confound the State of the Church, with the gouernment of it: forſooth becauſe Chriſt did adopt Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> for a Paſtor of the Church, and his Vicar, Iohn 21.15. he himſelfe being the abſolute King and Monarch thereof; therefore they conclude that abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and purely Monarchicall commaundement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs vnto Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> as being Chriſts lieftenant, And by and by that the Pope hath not only the whole Eccleſiaſticall power, but alſo all authoritie ouer the temporalty, indirectly at leaſt, and <hi>in ordine ad ſpiritualia, with relation to ſpirituall things,</hi> as the moſt reuerend Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> teacheth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they inferre that there is no need at all of holding Councells for the better and more holy gouernment of the Church, ſince the Lord hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vp vnto <hi>Peter</hi> ſolely and alone, the infalible authoritie and power to confirme his brethren. Luc. 22.32.</p>
            <p>Thirdly they conclude that if Councells bee aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſembled at any time, the Church neuer ſo lawfully gathered there hath no right at all to decide of any thing, the Pope being either abſent or not conſenting.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that the Pope may abrogate at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:3104:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>
all Canons of generall Councells concerning Eccleſiaſticall policie, and altogether diſanull them, and make all new.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, that the Pope hath not only power ouer all the particular Churches ſcattered ouer the world, but euen ouer the generall Councell, and that hee himſelfe is in no caſe ſubiect vnto the Councell.</p>
            <p>All which weake grounds it is moſt eaſie for any to beate downe, hauing once well conceiued of our former principles. For in the firſt place, they all aime but at this, to aſcribe that very ſame power to <hi>Peter,</hi> as the miniſteriall head, which only indeede belongs to one Chriſt alone, being Lord, and founder of the Church, which is ſophiſtically inferred <hi>a dicto ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer ad dictum ſecundum quid, from that which is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed ſimply, to that which is ſaid but in a manner.</hi> But, I pray you, is there not a great difference betweene the Maſter and the Steward, that is, betweene Chriſt and <hi>Peter?</hi> For the Church is by Chriſt, and for Chriſt; but <hi>Peter</hi> by the Church, and for the Church, as the eye by man, and for man.</p>
            <p>For confutation of their ſecond principle, you may reade it Sect. 7.</p>
            <p>The third, the fourth, and the fift, bee not worth anſwering, being all fallaciouſly inferred <hi>a dicto ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pliciter, ad dictum ſecundum quid, from that which is affirmed ſimply, to that which is ſaid but in a manner</hi> as though <hi>Peter</hi> had the ſame power ouer the Church, which Chriſt hath. And ſurely if we loue the truth, we muſt freely ſay that by nature a deſire is giuen to all men to be free and happie; but who may naturally bee
<pb facs="tcp:3104:29"/>
happy without freedome? But if the infallibilitie of decrecing, doe decide out in the Pope ſolely and a lone, no body then ſhall halfe the power of delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue voice in the aſſemblies of the Church, which is againſt the pleaſure of the Lord Matt. 18 18. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon looke our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Section. So that if this opinion take place, it followes that Chriſt hath ſuffered all his extremities only to ſubmit his Spouſe the Church, that is to ſay all Chriſtians, to the ſoueraigne Empire of the Pope Which is directly contrarie to the law of God and Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XV"/> But now becauſe of all the arguments of our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, three principally ſeem to be of ſom waight, we will alſo examine them. Firſt, that <hi>Peter</hi> hath been ordained by Chriſt, to bee the Sheep-heard ouer the whole Church, in theſe wordes. <hi>Feede my ſheepe,</hi> and that by that diuine ſpeech neither Apoſtles nor gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councels are excluded being all Chriſts ſheepe, and therefore to be fed by <hi>S. Peter</hi> the Vicar of Chriſt. To that we anſwere, that by theſe wordes Chriſt did giue no other authoritie but miniſteriall vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> as we haue proued Sect. 4.5. and 9. And that the duty of a Miniſter and Vicar is to put in execution the precepts of the Diuine, Naturall, and Canonicall law, but yet according to the rules of the Ariſtocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall temper ordained by God: And that therefore <hi>Peter</hi> is accounted a Paſtor, only for the execution of Canons, adminiſtration of the word, and other ſuch things, which may better be managed by one man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, then by the whole Church gathered together in a Councell.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:3104:30"/>Their ſecond argument is, That the whole Church gathered together in a Councell, makes but one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milie, one Flocke, one Kingdome, and viſible bodie of Chriſt; therefore muſt alſo neceſſarily haue a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble head, the Pope: and, it would ſeeme a ſtrange Monſter, if one bodie ſhould haue two ſupreme heads, the Pope, and the generall Councell. Wee anſwere, that the Church is a Monarchicall policie tempered by an Ariſtocraticall Gouernement. Whence of neceſſitie it followes that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell hath the ſupreme power for direction of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, correction, and authoritie, to make Canons; And as for <hi>Peter,</hi> hee hath it only for the execution, exerciſe, and vſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ies towardes the particular Churches. Looke our Sect. 4.5.6. and 9.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XVI"/> Thirdly, they alleage that in the Councell held at Rome vnder Pope <hi>Silueſter</hi> with 280. Biſhops it is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, cap. 20. <hi>Let no body iudge the firſt Sea, which is deſirous to temper iuſtice; The Iudge ſhall not bee iudged, no not of the Emperour, not of the whole Clergie, nor of King, nor of People.</hi> Which ſentence <hi>Gratia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> citeth 9. queſt. 3. <hi>Can. Nemo.</hi> But if wee muſt needes tell you what wee thinke thereof, whoſoeuer wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l duly conſider that Canon, ſhall euen at the firſt ſight perceiue that it is more hurtfull then fauoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the Aduerſaries; becauſe the opinion of the Schoole of Paris, grounded vpon the decree of the Synode of Conſtance, teaches, that the Pope may bee iudged by the Councell in that caſe only, when he doth notoriouſly ſcandalize the Church, and is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrigible.
<pb facs="tcp:3104:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
But if he be deſirous to temper iuſtice, truly he muſt be iudged of no body, ſince he law is not made againſt a i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> man, being a perpetuall law to himſelfe. Secondly, although this Canon ſhould decree abſolutely, yet can it not derogate any thing from the authoritie of the decrees of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Conſtance; ſince it was made in a particular Church, which indeede ought not to iudge of the Paſtor of the whole Church, vnleſſe hee ſubmit himſelfe to the iudgement of that Councell, as once Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the third did. 2. queſt. 4. <hi>Canon. Mandaſlis.</hi> Therefore thoſe wordes, <hi>No not of the whole Clergie,</hi> muſt hee vnderſtood diſtributiuely of ſome Church, or particular Clergie, but not ioynt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly of a whole generall Councell, as that of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, or Baſill was. Thirdly, who is acquainted with the reading of Councells, ſhall ſoone perceiue, that there are many harſh and vnproper thinges in this Canon, which make it iuſtly ſuſpected of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eption. For certainely in thoſe times the Fathers of the Church did not ſpeake ſo gloriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, neither did the perſecutions giue them leaue to thinke of any abſolute power. Moreouer, what needes to haue ſpoken of Kinges, ſince at that time there were none at all, but only the Romane Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors? But thou, Chriſtian Reader; we pray thee looke thereupon Cardinall <hi>Cuſanus. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. <hi>de concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantia Catholicas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For all other authoritie, which are cited out of the writings of Popes, &amp; read 9. queſt. 3. there is no great account to be made of them, ſince <hi>Iohn Gerſon,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:3104:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
other Pariſian Doctors doe anſwere in a word, That none is to be beleeued in his owne cauſe, except his teſtimonie agree with the Diuine, Naturall, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall law. But now it is contrarie to the law of God and Nature, that the miniſteriall head ſhould haue power ouer the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XVII"/> And ſurely the finall cauſe of the Church, which is euerlaſting life by a good gouernment, declares e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently, that the Pope is by the Church, and for the Church; not contrariwiſe, The Church by, and for the Pope. Therefore in the matter of Eccleſiaſticall gouernment, that <hi>Cephas,</hi> that was <hi>Peter,</hi> is ſubiect vnto the Church, as the eie vnto man. 1. Cor. 3.21. <hi>Therefore let no man glorie in men, for all thinges are yours.</hi> (that is of the Church) <hi>Whether it be</hi> Paul, <hi>or</hi> Apollos, <hi>or</hi> Cephas, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Item, 2. Cor. 13.10. <hi>All power is giuen to edification, not to deſtruction.</hi> From whence it ariſeth, as proued, that the Church by the Diuine, and Naturall law, can prouide, and preuent, that the Pope may not rule her to her owne deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, as it was decided <hi>Conc. Conſtant. Seſſ.</hi> 4. and 5.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="XVIII"/> Finally, whereas they crie ſo loud, that the Church hath an indirect authoritie ouer the Temporaltie, it is true by way of doctrine, perſwaſion, direction, and excluſion from the communion of the Church, but falſe that it ought to be done by conſtraint, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Princes, as we haue ſhewed Sect. 11. &amp; 12 Seeing the Church hath neither Territorie, nor vſe of the materiall ſword. Whoſoeuer therefore doe maintaine, that the Church may lawfully depoſe Chriſtian Princes, doe euen as much as if one ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:3104:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
inferre, that the Schoole-maſter, becauſe he hath the authoritie of Scholaſticall diſcipline, may diſinherite his Diſciples of their partrimonie, if they be obſtinate againſt his diſcipline; Which alſo is fallacious, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wreſted <hi>à dicto ſecundum quid, addictum ſimpliciter,</hi> from that which is ſaid in ſome reſpect, to that which is affirmed ſimply. For ſuch thinges which are true in ſome one and peculiar ſenſe, ought not to be ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to an vniuerſall and abſolute ſenſe, but by So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſters and Iuglers only. And if they vrge further that the Church is ſufficient in it ſelfe, and a ſupreme commandreſſe. The anſwere is, that that muſt be li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitted within thoſe bounds which be aſſigned by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to euery thing: But the eſſentiall cauſes of the Church, will not ſuffer that church-men ſhould med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with violent or ſecular buſineſſes. Wherefore all the ſufficiencie of the Church gouernment ought to be deriued from the obſeruation of the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, but not from any temporall Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, or right of ſword. Mat. 28.19. <hi>Goe therefore and teach all nations, baptizing them, and teaching them to obſerue all thinges whatſoeuer I haue commanded you, and lot I am with you alwaies vntill the end of the world.</hi> For the arguments which doe vphold this doctrine, wee will reduce them to three heads. The firſt ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine all the examples which <hi>Sanders, Bellarmine, Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queus,</hi> and others ſet forth out of the old Teſtament, but all <hi>ab ignoratione Elenchi,</hi> through vnskillfullneſſe of arguing. Who is ignorant among vs, that there is a farr different nature of the Iewes Sinagogue, and of the Chriſtian Church, of the law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and of
<pb facs="tcp:3104:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the Goſpell. For theſe indeede had Territorie allo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted them, &amp; conſequently might haue right of meere command from God; which no wiſe man will euer affirme of the Church. And to this that the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall law compared to that of <hi>Moſes,</hi> yea to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther law whatſoeuer, is a law truly Roiall and full of mildneſſe, and moſt perfect libertie, whereas the law of <hi>Moſes</hi> was a moſt ſeruile bondage, Act. 15.10. Gal. 4.3.</p>
            <p>The ſecond head offereth vnto vs the authorities taken out the Canonicall law, which Cardinall <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> commended, namely cap. 3. <hi>Synod. Lateran.</hi> where it is ordained that Kings and Princes are to be depoſed, which doe not roote out all Heretikes from their Dominions. The anſwere is, that theſe and the like ought to haue no more power againſt ciuill Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, then the extrauagant of <hi>Boniface</hi> 8. <hi>Vnam Sanctam,</hi> or the conſtitution of <hi>Paul</hi> 4. <hi>Cum ei Apoſtolatus of ſiue,</hi> which is to be read in the Directorie for Inquiſitors: ſeeing thoſe decrees haue been made not Synodical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that is, with conſent of the whole Church, but by the Popes priuately, and by their owne proper mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which therefore doe not binde, becauſe the Church is ruled by Canon, not by abſolute power. Sect. 5. and 8.</p>
            <p>For the third head; we denie abſolutely that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of King <hi>Chilperi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> or the tranſlation of the Empire to the French, was by the only authoritie of the Popes, without conſent, authoritie, or deſire of the people: And though it were true as they ſay, yet would it make but very little or nothing to the deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb facs="tcp:3104:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of our preſent Controuerſie, ſince it rather ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a queſtion <hi>of fact then of right;</hi> as alſo the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of the depoſing of <hi>Henrie</hi> 4. <hi>Frederick</hi> 2. and other Emperous or Kings. Let therefore our Aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries diſpute of right, not of fact: for our Lord Ieſus Chriſt hath ordained the Chriſtian commonwealth, to be gouerned by good manners, and Canons, not by examples.</p>
            <p>The ſolution of all other arguments drawen either from holy Scripture, or any where elſe, may be taken out of the moſt learned Treatiſe of M. <hi>Iohn</hi> of Paris touching Regall and Papall authoritie.</p>
            <p>Let all theſe thinges be ſubiect vnto the iudgement of the Catholike Church.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3104:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
